Preliminary Inventory to the Wolfgang Wilhelm Sauer Papers, 1913-1989
Hoover Institution Archives
- Part II
  - University Tenure, Search and Promotion Committee Files
  - Evaluation and review of manuscripts for publishers (returned to Department of History/UCB) (T 22- T 53)
  - "NY Times / Bitburg 1985"
  - Letter to editor and drafts (T 54)
  - "Review (books) FAZ, HZ" (Box 33.)
  - Book reviews and drafts (T 55)
  - "Review Hoffman and Steinert"
  - Book review and drafts (T 56)
  - "Taylor - History of Berlin Architecture"
  - Grant evaluation (T 57)
  - "Verlage"
  - Correspondence with publishers (T 58)
  - "IPSA"
  - Information (T 59)
  - "Historiker Verband"
  - Information, notes, correspondence (T 60)
  - "Ernst Reuter Gesellschaft"
  - Information, correspondence (T 61)
  - "Dt. Ver. Für Polit. Wissen."
  - Information, notes, correspondence (T 62)
  - "Ullstein Verlag"
  - Correspondence and reviews (T 63)
  - Manuscript: "Scheitern der parla. Monarchie" (belongs to November Revolution project)
  - Correspondence (U 1)
  - "Miscellaneous / 1967"
  - Notes and drafts on the theory of history (U 2)
  - "Heidegger"
  - Notes (U 3)
  - Xerox: "Weimar Culture: Experiments on Edge of Hope and Despair" (U 4)
  - Xerox: "Role of Jews in Weimar..." (see Manuscripts) (U 5)
  - History 285 exam. (U 6)
  - Answers for History 285 exam. (U 7)
  - Manuscript: "Prussia in German Historiography" (U 8)
  - Research project description 1972 (same as L 13) (U 9)
  - Manuscript: "Facing the Destroyed Past..." (see Manuscripts) (U 10)
  - Manuscript: "Experiment d. parla. Monarchie" (belongs to November Revolution project) (U 11)
  - Miscellaneous papers: junk mail, poem, letters to Dr. Sauer (incl. unopened mail); notes; papers pertaining to classes; papers from UCB; Tenure Committee; requests from UCB for grades (U 13) (Box 34.)
  - "Finished Business"
  - Information one L. Baeck Institute; letters; Xerox of table of contents (possibly November Revolution project) (U 14)
  - "Urgent Business"
  - Lebenslauf/Résumé; letters; UCB miscellaneous; reading list History 104 notes (U 15)
  - Organization outline on November Revolution (U 16)
  - Reprint: "Nat'l. Soc.: Totalitarianism or Fascism?" (U 17)
  - Clipped articles and notes (U 18)
  - Clipped articles and notes (U 19)
  - Collected clipping pasted on sheets: 1963 (U 20 - U 29) (Box 35-36.)
  - Freie Univ. Berlin documents (Studienbuch; etc.) (Box 36.)
  - Notes; handwritten story "Drei Pferdediebe"; correspondence with Univ. Marburg (W 1)
  - Manuscript: "Facing Destroyed Past" (see Manuscripts)
  - Correction copy of above (different version
  - Notes; Hist.280 biblio (W 2)
  - Institute letter 1962; activity report (Tätigkeitsbericht) (W 3)
  - Correspondence with Spiegel's R. Augstein (W 4)
  - "Foundations Grant"
  - Research project reports; grant information and correspondence (W 5)
  - Book reviews
  - Manuscript: "Before the Deluge: A Portrait of Berlin"
  - Drafts (W 6)
  - "Encyclopedia Americana"
  - Correspondence and drafts concerning encyclopedia articles on Germany 1933-1945, Gestapo and Nazism (W 7)
  - "Encyclopedia American - Biograph. Articles"
  - Correspondence and drafts: Hitler, Eichmann, Hess, Goerdeler, Göring, Goebbels, Gestapo (W 8)
  - "Ritter/Craig" (Box 37.)
  - Manuscript: review of Craig's Prussian Army and Ritter's Staatskunst; notes and drafts (W 9)
  - Manuscript (as in W 9); drafts and notes (W 10)
  - "Vortrag Marburg 1962"
  - Manuscript: "Militärpolitik in der Weimarer Republik."
  - Correspondence, drafts and notes (W 11)
  - "Bundeswhr"
  - Manuscript: "Militärismus in der Bundesrepublik?"
  - Biblio. (for above article); correspondence, clipped articles, notes (W 12)
  - Manuscript: "Zum Stand der militärpolitischen Forschung in der Bundesrepublik"; copies, drafts, notes (W 13)
  - (new folder)
  - Manuscripts:
    - "The Economic and Cultural Role of Jews in the Weimarer Republik"
    - "Ein republikanischer General?"
  - Four chapters for Nov. Rev. (on Soldatenräte, Berliner Aktion, Reichskonferenz, Niederlage - see R 10) (W 14)
  - "Nov. Rev. - Bündniß Groener-Ebert / Durchschlag"
  - Systematically bound chapters: Introd., chapt. 1-11 (W 15)
  - "Nov. Rev..."
  - Part III. (Does not include chapters from W 14) (W 16)
  - (inaccurate title)
  - Reading notes and Xerox (W 17)
  - "TH - Darmstadt" (Box 38.)
  - Correspondence, notes, employment with Hessen (W 18)
  - "Neuauflagen"
  - Notes; copies of review articles; clipped articles; manuscript by W. Hofer (W 19)
  - "Ältere Arbeiten"
  - Older articles bound together:
    - "Die Franz. Revol. und das Problem der Massengesellsch"
    - "Probleme der Revol." (1st and 2nd versions)
    - "Zum Verhältniß Groener-Schleicher"
  - Outline of broadcast on Hitler
  - Notes on presentations given (W 20)
  - Manuscript: "Das Problem des deutschen Nationalstaates"
  - Draft and correspondence (W 26)
  - "Ritter/Craig"
  - Notes (W 27)
  - "Theory of History (and Paul Rosenberg Festschrift)"
  - Manuscript: "History and the Social Sciences"
  - Notes, drafts, Xerox articles (W 28)
  - "Rosenberg"
  - Xerox articles (W 33)
  - G. Motzkin dissertation
  - "Z"
  - Papers by J. Zammito (Y 1)
  - Student papers, dissertations, recommendations
- Part III
  - Folders labeled A A (Box 39-43.)
    - 22 folders with notes, drafts, archive extracts and book reviews relating to the Reichswehr, Weimar, the rise of the National Socialists in 1933 (possibly old folders relating to Mobilmachung manuscript)
    - Other folders:
      - "Institutskorrespondenz 1950-1963"
      - Wilhelm Sauer Affairs (uncle of Prof. Wolfgang Sauer)
      - "Alfred H. Fried/Encycl.Brit." (article and draft)
      - "Geschichte I: Prähistorie/Seminararbeit Hartung" (school notes 1939)
      - "Konisch: Hölderlin" (univ. notes 1949)
      - "Bism. Reich" (notes)
      - Manuscript (not pulled): "Die Geschichte und Organis. der militärischen Gliederung der NSDAP"
      - "Schriftwechsel 1950"
      - "Hausbau"
      - "General Nollet: Une Expèrience de Désarmement" (notes)
      - "Deutsche Literatur: Zeitalter des Humanismus. Prof. Neuwald" (univ. notes 1949/1950)
      - "Nationalstaat" (notes)
      - "Geschichte II: Altertum und Antike" (1949)
      - "Seminar Prof. Stammer" (1954/1956)
      - "Soziologie des Militärs und des Kampfes"
      - "Militarismus: Alphabetische Bibliographie"
      - "Militarismus: Fischer Lexikon" (article and notes)
      - Manuscript (not pulled): "Die Mobilmachung der Gewalt 1933-1934"; chapters 1 and 2
      - "Philosophie" (notes)
      - "Geschichte IV. Sonstiges" (univ. notes)
      - "Geschichte: Grundlagen"
      - Machtergreifung: Rezensionen
    - Collection of printed pages: copy of 1918 German Cabinet protocols
    - Photographs (sent to Juliane Lohnert, Prof. Sauer's niece)
  - Folders labeled A B (Box 44-48.)
    - 21 folders of notes, transcripts, archival extracts on Reichswehr
    - Other folders:
      - "Fischer Lexikon" (encyclop. Article)
      - "Wegweiser durch die Publikationen über den Nürnberger Hauptkriegsverbrecherprozeß"
      - "Onkel Willy" (correspondence: returned to Juliane Lohnert)
      - Manuscript: " Der Anteil des Adels am Offizierstand der Reichswehr" (2 similar folders: one pulled and placed in manuscript box)
      - "Zeitgeschichte"
      - "Militarismus"
      - "Widerstand"
      - Manuscript: "Schweizerische Neutralität und deutsche Neutralisierung" (place in manuscript box)
      - Manuscript: "Die Entstehung der Reichswehr 1919-1920: Ein Beitrag zum Problem des Militarismus in der Demokratie" (placed in manuscript box)
      - FU Studentenverein
      - Geschichte: Mittelalter, Renaiss., Neuzeit.
      - Bracher/Machtergreifung (2 folders of notes, manuscript copies, reviews)
      - "Institute für politische Wissenschaften / Entwürfe" (notes)
      - "Militärsoziologie: Entwürfe Winter 1960-61" (manuscript notes)
      - Clausewitz (text and notes)
      - "Politische Wissenschaft. Allgeimen"
      - "Nationalstaat/Stammer" (drafts and notes)
      - Manuscript: "Die Entstehung des deutschen Nationalstaats und das Problem der Revolution in Deutschland" (placed in manuscript box)
      - "Institute. Allgemeines"
      - "Literatur zur Geschichte"
    - Concert programs and music scores
  - Folders labeled A C (Box 49-52.)
    - Grey file box: "Nazi Elite" - biographical file cards
    - Small and thin file folders (from 1937 to 1941), all containing handwritten notes from university lectures:
      - "N S Literatur"
      - "S S (Sommersemester) 1941 Marburg Professor Traeger"
      - "Griechische Geschichte"
      - "Römische Geschichte"
      - "Platon und Athen"
      - "Geographisches Proseminar"
      - "Historische Geologie"
      - "Got. Grammatik"
      - "Prof. Mommsen: Von Bismarck bis zum Weltkrieg 1890-1918" (1941)
      - "Mommsen: Allgemeine Geschichte 1815-1862" (1940)
      - "Holtzmann: Allgemeine Geschichte 900-1250"
      - "Alfred von Wegerer: Bibliographie zur Vorgeschichte des Weltkrieges; Auszüge 1938"
      - "Merkblätter" (clipped and pasted newspaper articles)
      - "Holtzmann: Geschichte zur Zeit der Völkerwanderung"
      - "Keinast: Mittelalterliches Proseminar"
      - "Mayer: Seminar (Albrecht I)"
      - "Arbeitsgemeinschaft Fränkische Siedlung"
      - "Rörig: Übung zur Geschichte Heinr. I und Otto I"
      - "Rörig: Allgemeine Geschichte im frühen Mittelalter"
      - "Renaissance: Zettelkatalog"
      - "Prof. Hamann: Dürer"
      - "Plinius: Übersetzungsübungen"
      - "Aufsätze zur Vorgeschichte"
      - "Renaissance: Literaturauszug"
      - "Geschichte des 30 jährigen Krieges"
      - "Schüßler: Fr. Revolution und Befreiungskriege"
      - "Der indogermanische Sprachkreis"
      - "Mitzka: Altgermanische Dichtung"
      - "Berthold: Mittelhochdeutsche Übungen"
      - "Mittelhochdeutsch"
      - "Wolff: Mittelhochdeutsche Dichtung II"
    - Black notebooks (containing handwritten notes):
      - "Geschichte der deutschen Literatur im vorklassischen Zeitalter; Prof. Petersen 1939"
      - "Staat und Erziehung in Deutschland: 1700 - Gegenawrt"
      - "Aufsätze" (1937-1938)
      - "Deutsche Kunst im Mittelalter"
      - "Die Aufgaben der Hitlerjugend"
      - "Landsknecht und Soldat des Volksheeres"
      - "Führertum und Gefolgschaftstreue in Goethe's Götz"
      - "Hat der Mensch freien Willen oder nicht?"
      - "Gedanken über die Ostlandfrage"
      - "Allgemeine Geschichte zur Zeit der Völkerwanderung - Holtzmann"
      - "Malerei"
      - "Birt: von Homer bis Sokrates" (2 folders)
      - "Philosophie der Geschichte als Selbstkritik der Kultur"
    - Small notebook: "Das Königsgrab von Seddin" (original sent to Juliane Lohnert; Xerox copy added for archive file)
    - Large folders:
      - 20 folders of notes, transcripts, occasional letters on National Socialist research
      - Transcripts of radio broadcast series "Der Nationalsozialismus: Anspruch und Wirklichkeit" including: "Führer der Bewegung" by Dr. Sauer and Dr. Brigitte Granzow
      - 4 folders: Papers and correspondence of Dr. Wilhelm Sauer; condolence letters regarding his death
      - Manuscript folders:
        - "Die Mobilmachung der Gewalt"
        - "Auflösung der Weimarer Republik. Kapitel 10."
        - "Clausewitz und das Problem des `absoluten Krieges`" (2 folders)
        - "Soziale Zusammensetzung des Offizierkorps der Reichswehr 1920-1932" (placed in manuscript box)
        - Untitled: manuscript deals with relationship between politics and the military; possibly relates to Clausewitz
    - Periodicals and Literature-catalogues from early 1960's
    - Photographic equipment catalogues
  - Folders labeled A D (Box 53-57.)
    - "Anmerkungen 1933/1934 1. Fassung" (2 folders)
    - "Entwurf 1933/1934"
    - "Org. Soziologie"
    - "Planung"
    - Miscellaneous notes
    - "Moderne Kunst" (2 folders; clipped articles)
    - Tübingen Convention / Paper held
    - "Vortrag ASTA Marburg 1955/1962"
    - "Krieg und Frieden" (essay and notes)
    - "Wehrverfassung"
    - Manuscript: "Die Mobilmachung der Gewalt 1933-1934" (4 folders)
    - Miscellaneous notes
    - "SFB/NDR II. Programm" (notes for broadcast)
    - Manuscript: "Die Reichswhehr. I. Fassung" (3 folders)
    - Manuscript: "Die Entstehung der Reichswehr 1918-1921" (3 folders)
    - Manuscript: "Die Auflösung der Weimarer Republik. IX. Kapitel Die Reichswehr" (plus published copy)
    - "Militarismus" (diverse contents)
    - "Methode" (Auflösung d. Weimarer Repk. Printed election studies)
    - "Militarismus. Chronolog. Entwicklung 1807-1945" (notes by year; incomplete)
    - "Nürnberger Dokumente" (6 folders)
    - "Militarismus. Atlantik-Brücke" (letters to publisher, notes, collected essays)
    - Manuscript: "Militarismus in der Bundesrepublik?" (placed in manuscript box)
    - "Militarismus. Psychologie"
    - "Militarismus. Soziologie"
    - "Alphabetisches Personenverzeichniß zur Dissertation 1950"
    - "Clausewitz"
    - Manuscript: "Was ist Militarismus?" (placed in manuscript box)
    - "Alt-Berlin" (clipped articles)
    - "Dusterberg: (Neue Deutsche Biographie essay)
    - "N S Südwestfunk" (broadcast working manuscript and notes)
    - "SWF" (correspondence and notes)
    - Collected clipped articles
  - Folders labeled A E (Box 58.)
    - Miscellaneous papers from Dr. Wilhelm Sauer (Prof. Sauer's uncle) including:
      - "Verlagsverträge"
      - Documents on bomb damage to home
      - Military government questionnaire
    - Ring binders (Box 58-59.)
      - Untitled: Military-political research; typed notes
      - "Geschichte / Literatur." Notes on lectures and seminars of Professors: Berges, Rosenberg, Herzfeld, Leisegang, Kunisch, Altenberg (names of professors for 3 sections not deciphered)
      - "Militarismus Theorie" (reading and outline notes)
      - "Philosophie." Notes on seminars of Professors: Leisegang, Piper, Hartmann, Litt, Herzfeld
      - Untitled. Diverse early essays (1939-1951) including: "Die Doppelte Wurzel der Idee allgemeinen Volksbewaffnung." (placed in manuscript box)
  - Folders labeled A F (Appears to contain items primarily from Dr. Wilhelm Sauer - uncle of Prof. Wolfgang Sauer) (Box 60-62.)
  - Periodicals
    - Deutsche Kolonialzeitung 1914
    - Europa Archiv 1946-1947
    - Die Gegenwart 1946-1947
    - Forschungen und Fortschritte 1947-1948
    - Göttinger Universitätszeitung 1947
    - Die Schöpfung 1946-1947
    - Zeitschrift für Kunst 1947-1948
    - Das Kunstwerk 1946-1948
    - Die Kunst 1942-1943
    - Files:
      - "Onkel Willy" (correspondence)
      - "Kunst 1949" (clipped articles)
      - "Pf" (clipped articles and notes relating to philosophy)
      - "Neue Aufgaben. W.R.Politik" (collected articles on European union and politics)
      - "Forschung" (collected notes, articles, poem; letter to publisher - all most likely pertaining to Wilhelm Sauer)
      - "Geschichte Barbara Sauer" (World War I military papers of Oberleutnant Wilhelm Sauer)
      - "Menschenschicksale. Exemplar II. Druckfähig 1959" (notes and manuscript of Wilhelm Sauer)
      - Folders of files, most likely from Wilhelm Sauer:
        - "Haushälterin" (applications)
        - "A.T. / Reform Organ." (criminal law)
        - "Einf."
        - "Altes Material"
        - 12 additional small folders (from Wilhelm Sauer)
    - Envelope: photograph; "Danksagung" (birthday 1949); "Zum 70. Geburtstag 1949"
    - Miscellaneous papers (travel brochures, newspapers; postcards)
    - Folder: "Germanistik" Rilke (Steinmetz); Geschichte d. dtn. Sprache (Ludwig) (probably notes taken by Wolfgang Sauer)
    - Drawings (sent to Juliane Lohnert)
  - Folders labeled B A (This box contains unsorted papers from the study) (Box 63-66.)
    - Publications:
      - Die Deutsche Inflation (1982)
      - Articles for 6th World Congress on Federalism
      - Ostprobleme (1965-1966)
      - BDR Bulletins (1964-1965)
      - Deutsches Reichsheer (1913)
    - Folders:
      - "Research project 1967/1968" (on crisis of German cosmopolitanism - placed in manuscript box)
      - "Curtis project" (historians' workshop)
      - "AHA Paper" (NS: Totalitarianism or Fascism? 1965-1966)
      - "Students political activity / Vietnam" (flyers)
      - "Students political activity / general" (flyers)
      - "Univer. politics / faculty 1969-1970" (flyers and notes)
      - "Univer. politics / faculty and students 1968-1969" (flyers)
      - "Univer. politics / students 1969-1970" (flyers)
      - "Xerox copies" (miscellaneous articles)
      - "Geheimes Tagebuch 1965" (sent to Juliane Lohnert)
      - "Cambodian crisis"
      - "Recordings"
      - "Berlin Register"
      - "Soldatenräte" (1960 RIAS broadcast)
      - "Gillingham" (student file returned to Dept. of History / UCB)
      - "Fragments / Ideas / Materials"
      - "Walter Dehme: Damals in der Reichskanzlei - Auszüge" (1958)
      - German History 1815-1890
    - Diverse Xerox articles, including Fritz Reuter: "Wie ich zu einer Frau kam"
    - Manuscript excerpt: November Revolution
    - Prof. Sauer class notes 103 (1965-1967); 201
    - Miscellaneous notes
    - Notes from Wilhelm Sauer
  - Manuscripts (Box 66-68.)
    - Major projects
      - A. German History
        - 1. Completed set: chapters 1-6
          - Introduction
            - 1. What is "German" History?
            - 2. When does German History Begin?
            - 3. Where is Germany?
            - 4. (no title)
            - 5. The Natural Environment of German History
          - Chapter 1: The Prehistoric Peoples of the North
            - 1. Who were the Germani?
            - 2. Tribal Cultures in Prehistoric Central Europe
              - Celts and Rhenish Germani
              - The East Elbians
            - 3. Origins of Archaic Kingship
            - 4. The Suebic Kingdom
          - Chapter 2: Rome and its attempted Conquest of Germania 55 B.C. to A.D. 9
          - Chapter 3: Roman Frontier Policy A.D. 14 - c. 160
          - Chapter 4: The Tribal Kingdoms and the Great Invasions
            - 1. The "Royal" Tribes
            - 2. The Migrations
            - 3. Raids and Invasions
            - 4. Rome and the Invasions
            - 5. The Proto-German Tribes
          - Prologue II: Christianization
          - Chapter 5: Medieval Christianity
          - Chapter 6: The Franks and the Irish Mission c. 500-700
            - 1. The Conversion of the Franks and the Rise of the Frankish Kingdom, sixth and seventh centuries
            - 2. The Celtic Church and the Irish Mission-7th C
        - 2. Fragments
          - a. Outline plan for the German History Project
          - b. Additional chapter not bound: Chapter 7: Boniface and the Anglo-Saxon Mission c. 690-750
            - 1. The Anglo-Saxon Church
            - 2. The Crisis of the Merovingian Kingdom
            - 3. St. Boniface and His Early Work (716-741)
            - 4. Another Church Reform 740-754
            - 5. The Rise of the Carolingian Kingdom
          - c. Additional chapters, with older annotation of "Hist. Civil. Germ."
            - Chapter 8: The Jewish Origins of Christianity
            - Chapter 9: Jesus
            - Chapter 10: Origins 911-962
          - d. Miscellaneous sections, filed by Dr. Sauer in same drawer
            - 1. The Birth of Classical Humanism
            - 2. Classical Anthropology
            - 3. Freedom and Slavery in Classical Humanism
          - e. Diverse introductions for this project (on civilization, on the intent of the work; etc.)
          - f. Conclusion (a 3-page draft)
      - B. Das Bündniß Ebert-Groener
        - 1. Project description: "Werbetext zu: Militär-und Zivilgewalt in der Revolution: Das Bündniß Groener-Ebert 1918" (2 1/4 pages)
        - 2. Inaugural Dissertation: "Das Bündniß Ebert-Groener: Eine Studie über Notwendigkeit und Grenzen der militälischen Macht: (FU Berlin 1956). This manuscript has corrections and revisions on it which were apparently added later
        - 3. Plan for the project - which calls for 10 Parts and 32 chapters. (These do not entirely match completed set)
        - 4. Completed set, bound: November-Revolution: Das Bündniß Ebert-Groener, chapters 1-15
          - Einleitung (60 pp)
            - 1. Die November-Revolution in der Forschung
            - 2. Fragestellung und Abgrenzung des Themas
            - 3. Bemerkungen zur Typologie der Revolution
            - 4. Militär-und Zivilgewalt in der Revolution
          - I. Teil.: Der Weltkrieg 1914-1918 als revolutionärer Prozeß
            - 1. Kap.: Die Kriegszielproblematik
            - 2. Kap.: Der Kriegsausbruch un die Politik des schnellen Sieges
            - 3. Kap.: Der Übergang zum Festungskrieg 1915-1916
            - 4. Kap.: Die Diktatur Ludendorffs und die Friedensresolution
            - 5. Kap.: Sozialismus und Krieg in Deutschland 1914-1918
            - 6. Kap.: Der militärische Zusammenbruch
          - II. Teil: Versuch zur Rettung der Monarchie: Die Oktoberreform 1918
            - 7. Kap.: Die Revolution von oben
            - 8. Kap.: Die Reformregierung
            - 9. (no title)
            - 10.Kap.: Das Experiment der parlamentarischen Monarchie und sein Scheitern
            - 11.Kap.: Das Scheitern der parlamentarischen Monarchie
          - III. Teil: Die Novemberrevolution
            - 12.Kap.: Der Volksaufstand 2. bis 9. November
            - 13.Kap.: Der Kampf um die Führung der Revolution
            - 14.Kap.: Die Einigung der Arbeiterklasse
            - 15.Kap.: Das Bündniß Groener-Ebert
        - 5. Completed set, unbound: chapter titles without chapter numbers
          - Kap.: Der Kampf um die Soldatenräte
          - Kap.: Die Berliner Aktion der Heeresleitung
          - Kap.: Die Reichskonferenz der Arbeiter- und Soldatenräte
          - Kap.: Die Niederlage des Feldheeres und der Sieg des Offiziercorps
        - 6. Additional manuscripts found
          - IV. Teil: Das Problem der Revolutionsarmee
            - 1. Das Beispiel Österreichs
            - 2. Eberts Militärpolitik
            - 3. Die revolutionären Wehren in Berlin
        - 7. Fragments
          - a. Sozialökonomische Probleme der Nov.-Revolution
          - b. Exkurs: Zum Problem der Dolchstoß-Legende
          - c. (Exkurs) Das Problem der Kriegsziele und der Wechsel der Obersten Heeresleitung 1916
          - d. (Exkurs) Die Plünderung des Berliner Schlosses und die Volksmarine Division
          - e. Exkurs: Über die politische Haltung des deutschen Westheeres am 9. November 1918
          - g. November-Revolution: Ms. Ammerkungen
        - 8. Related articles
          - a. "Der Anteil des Adels am Ofizierkorps der Reichswehr"
          - b. "Soziologische Zusammensetzung des Offizierkorps der Reichswehr"
          - c. "Die Entstehung der Reichswehr 1919-1920"
          - d. "Ein republikanischer General?"
      - C. Die Interessengruppen-Gesellschaft: Versuche einer historisch-soziologischen Begründung des Pluralismus
      - D. The New Amazons: An Essay on Women's Liberation
    - II. Other Manuscripts
      - "Über Don Juan" (1987)
      - "Frederick's Attack on Silesia 1740 - A Reexamination" (1983)
      - Historiographic Articles:
        - "The Economic and Cultural Role of Jews in the Weimar Republic"
        - "Facing the Destroyed Past: West German Historiography after 1945" (3 versions)
        - "Über die gegenwärtige Krise der deutschen Geschichte"
        - "Die Geistesgeschichte der Weimarer Republik als Forschungsproblem"
        - "History and the Social Science"
        - "Prussia in German Historiography after 1945"
        - "Before the Deluge: A Portrait of Berlin in the 1920's" (review)
      - "Juden und Christen" (1987)
      - "Kap Hoorn: Über Heldentum" (1987)
      - Articles on Militarism
        - "Die politische Geschichte der deutschen Armee und das Problem des Militarismus"